<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Dhruv Doshi</title>
 <link href="https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/blog/"/>
 <updated>2021-11-07T14:50:08-04:00</updated>
 <id>https://dhruvdoshi.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Dhruv Doshi</name>
   <email>dhruvdoshi25071999@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>What are weakness of Blockchain??(Everything isn't perferct!!)</title>
   <link href="https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/blog/2019/12/01/what-are-weaknes-of-blockchain"/>
   <updated>2019-12-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/2019/12/01/what-are-weaknes-of-Blockchain</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;1. There is no customer protection on the blockchain&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; Blockchain  technology operates as a push-based settlement system. This means the  individual holds power over the resource they want to verify on the  blockchain. This could be in cryptos, certificate authentication, land  titles, etc. The problem with this is if a transaction goes sour after  it has already been verified on the blockchain, the only feasible way of  returning the transaction is if the parties agree to reverse it. Using a  centralized system like a bank. However, there is a procedure in place  to be able to dispute trades after they are complete.Some  trade technologies that settle on a blockchain have used an arbiter  system to fix this problem, an example of this is the Open Bazaar P2P  trade network. This way a trade occurs between two people, and one  impartial moderator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;2. Settlement on a blockchain is slow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; A  cost of settling a transaction on the blockchain is that all the nodes  in the network need to come to an agreement that the transaction is  valid. This is a far slower process than having a bank verify your  transaction in an instant.Transactions  can be made instantaneously, however until the block in which the  transaction is inserted in has been verified, it is classified is  untrustworthy. In the time between a lodged transaction is made and when  the block settles, a bad actor could launch fraudulent transactions to  trick the network into what is known as double spend.A  very exciting upcoming technology that could solve this problem is the  lightning network. This solution acts as a layer 2 of blockchain  technology; it can be applied to any public blockchain. It will enable  instantly verified transactions for a fraction of the cost of today’s  settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;3. Miners can be selfish &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;The  mining process on the blockchain is an innovation which uses game  theory economics to incentivise people to commit computer power for  securing the network for a profit. The down-side of this is generally  miners won’t care about settling as many transactions as possible; they  will make the most money by finding and verifying a block in the fastest  way possible.This  leads to a problem of miners finding empty blocks and validating. There  is also another problem known as Selfish Mining, which is a situation  where a miner or mining pool finds and validates a block and does not  publish and distribute a valid solution to the rest of the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;4. The growing blockchain size &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; With  every new block, a blockchain grows. This can be an issue because each  node that is validating the network needs to store the entire history of  the blockchain in order to be a participant. This is a hard enough  problem with the bitcoin blockchain where the transaction size is only a  few bytes, the total blockchain size as of January 2017 is 98GB. Given  that at the same time in 2016 the size was 50GB, and the use of the  blockchain is continuing to increase, this is a growing concern.One  of the biggest debates in the bitcoin space is if the block size should  be increased. If a blockchain has bigger blocks the blockchain size  will increase faster, thus weeding out the solo miners eventually. This  is a big issue because the health of a blockchain network is partially  dependent on the amount of nodes in the network, and the spread of those  nodes across the world. The counter argument for this issue is that  with sufficient advancement of technology hard disk space will be very  cheap in the future and will stay ahead of the blockchain size. The  debate is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;5. Eventually settlement on the blockchain will not be cheap &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; On  any public blockchain, space in a block is a finite resource.  Necessarily as the network is utilized more the amount of transactions  that will want to settle in a block will exceed the storage capacity.  Public blockchain networks have a solution built in for this which is  that transactions with a higher miner fee attached will get precedence  to be included in a block. This makes sense because the miners want to  maximize their profit so that they will include transactions with the  highest fees first.This  is not a bug, but a feature. If it were free to settle on the  blockchain, there would be far too many ways of attacking the blocks  with dust transactions and clogging up the network. Originally the  bitcoin blockchain had no block size limit; this was eventually set to  1MB to avoid a Sybil Attack on the network.All  of these problems have potential solutions that can be implemented as a  fix. In my view blockchains will eventually have layers of  centralisation like the lightning network. However, this is not a bad  thing so long as there is a sufficient amount of encryption to protect  the privacy of the people who want to use the centralized layers of the  network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;REFERENCES&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blaetti, Robert. “5 Weak Points of Blockchain Technology.” Blockgeeks, 13 Jan. 2017, blockgeeks.com/public-blockchain/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‌&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What if we combine Blockchain and Cloud Computing ?</title>
   <link href="https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/blog/2019/10/31/what-if-we-combine-blockchain-and-cloud"/>
   <updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00-03:00</updated>
   <id>https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/2019/10/31/What-if-we-combine-blockchain-and-cloud</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Blockchain technology is distributed ledger with records of data containing all details of the transaction carried out and distributed among the nodes present in the network. All the transactions carried out previously are &lt;strong&gt;saved and then they are reflected&lt;/strong&gt; in the next upcoming block hash. Hence it is an &lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;intangible and immutable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; data structure at the basic end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloud computing is well-defined technology that emerged from &lt;strong&gt;large-scale distributed computing technology&lt;/strong&gt;. Cloud computing helps to reduce the burden on the resources and lets the user use the optimum resources for redundant work. Organizations like Google or Microsoft have large data servers and then the employees could get the required resources out of it. This helps the organization to have the flexibility of resources according to the projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some evident issues in cloud computing which are Data Security, Data Management, Interoperability etc. By having the Blockchain concept with the cloud we could solve all of the issues or &lt;strong&gt;technical bottlenecks&lt;/strong&gt; which we are facing at the moment with cloud computing. Blockchain technology is an emerging technology well known for its &lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;security and authenticity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, which are the main characteristics that are making the world turn to its side. By integrating blockchain with cloud computing, there will be many advantages in usability, trust, security, scalability, data management, and many other advantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several projects and Ideas which are working progressively in this direction, those are added in the references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;REFERENCES&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C. V. N. U. B. Murthy, M. L. Shri, S. Kadry and S. Lim, “Blockchain Based Cloud Computing: Architecture and Research Challenges,” in IEEE Access, vol. 8, pp. 205190-205205, 2020, doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2020.3036812.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nate Nead, “Blockchain’s Next Frontier: Cloud Computing?,” InvestmentBank.com, 09-Jun-2018. [Online]. Available: https://investmentbank.com/blockchain-cloud-computing/. [Accessed: 17-Oct-2021]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anna, “Blockchain vs Cloud Computing: Best Features for Corporate Space,” Gbksoft.com, 05-May-2021. [Online]. Available: https://gbksoft.com/blog/blockchain-vs-cloud-best-features-for-corporate-space/. [Accessed: 17-Oct-2021]
‌&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Where could be Blockchian be used ?</title>
   <link href="https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/blog/2019/10/01/where-could-be-blockchain-used"/>
   <updated>2019-10-01T00:00:00-03:00</updated>
   <id>https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/2019/10/01/Where-could-be-Blockchain_used</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Blockchain is freaking exciting and does have the potential to transform all of the business and how it operates, but that doesn’t mean it’s the right solution for every scenario. Here’s why you should choose blockchain  over, say, a standard outdated Centralized database:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;When you want to manage and secure digital relationships or keep a decentralized, shared system of record.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; Anytime you want to keep a long-term, transparent record of assets (for example, to record property or land rights ), publically available data, blockchain could be the ideal solution. Smart contracts, in particular, are great for facilitating digital relationships and transactions. With a solidity smart contract, automated payments can be released when parties in a  transaction agree that their conditions have been met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Anywhere a middleman or gatekeeper function is expensive or time-consuming.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; For  example, major cloud services nowadays allows user to pile up the data on the servers which are organized by a single body or corporate like Google or Amazon, these services charges immensely instead of the single data serves system we could use decentralized systems like DCS-BBN or SIA data systems which are backed by the blockchain and have an ecosystem of the hosts and consumers which provides storage for the rent on lower tariffs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;When you want to record secure transactions, especially between multiple partners.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; A  traditional database may be good for recording simple transactions between two parties, but when things get more complicated, blockchain can reduce bottlenecks and simplify relationships. For example, shipping conglomerate Maersk is working with IBM to develop a private blockchain platform to connect its various partners and customers across the shipping industry. What’s more, the added security of a decentralized system makes blockchain ideal for transactions in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Where the data is in constant flux, but you want to keep a record of past actions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;  Blockchain is a better, safer way to record the activity and keep data fresh while maintaining a record of its history. The data can’t be  corrupted by anyone or accidentally deleted, and you benefit from both a  historical trail of data, plus an instantly up-to-date record&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;REFERENCES&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benjamin, Neeraj. “Why Blockchain Makes the Difference?” BitsNBlocks, Blockchain Technology, Cryptocurrency, Bitcoins, ICO, Bitcoin, Blockchain Basics, Learning Zone, Crypto Bank, 22 Feb. 2021, bitsnblocks.co/why-blockchain-makes-the-difference/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‌Benjamin, Neeraj. “Why Blockchain Makes the Difference?” BitsNBlocks, Blockchain Technology, Cryptocurrency, Bitcoins, ICO, Bitcoin, Blockchain Basics, Learning Zone, Crypto Bank, 22 Feb. 2021, bitsnblocks.co/why-blockchain-makes-the-difference/.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What is Blockchain?</title>
   <link href="https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/blog/2019/08/31/what-is-blockchain"/>
   <updated>2019-08-31T00:00:00-03:00</updated>
   <id>https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/2019/08/31/What-is-Blockchain-!</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Blockchain is the technology that allows the user to &lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;create a decentralized system of transaction and data transfers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. For the naïve person, it is a method to create a people’s bank without central banks! Blockchain technology is used in the backend for each cryptocurrency. Talking about that, Blockchain is building the blocks of every critical data and then chaining the blocks. So if the last block or any previous block is changed or updated, then every information in the chain needs to be updated. This makes blockchain technology secure and more robust compared to other technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blockchain is a &lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;shared, immutable ledger that felicitates the process of recording transactions and tracking assets in a business network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. An investment can be tangible (a house or a car) or intangible (Intellectual property, patents, or copyrights). Virtually anything of value can be tracked and traded on a blockchain network, reducing risk and cutting costs for all involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Blockchain is a growing list of records, called blocks linked together with cryptography which is also described as “trustless and fully decentralized peer to peer immutable data storage which is spread over the network of participants often referred to as the nodes. Every block contains a &lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;cryptographic hash of the previous block and the timestamp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, and the transaction data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, let’s get back to basics. What is Blockchain, and how does it work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A blockchain is a file for storing data. Or, to put it in more technical terms, it’s an open, distributed database system. The data is distributed (i.e., duplicated), and the whole Blockchain is entirely decentralized. This means no one person or entity  (say, a government or corporation like Google or Microsoft) has control over the Blockchain;  this is a radical departure from the centralized (Government databases) databases controlled and administered by businesses and other entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does it work? In straightforward terms, the file consists of blocks of data, with each block being connected to the previous block with the hashing code,  forming a chain. Hence, the name &lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;“blockchain.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; As well as the data itself, each block also contains a record of when that block was created or edited. It contains the hash code of the previous block, which makes it very useful for maintaining a complex system of records that cannot be corrupted or lost, and this is the primary use case to preserve the integrity of the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the whole Blockchain is duplicated across many computers,  any user can view the entire Blockchain in the case of public blockchains. Transactions or records are processed not by one central administrator but by a network of users who work to verify the data and achieve a consensus; these verifiers are known as miners, each miner is paid some cryptocurrency for successful mining. If this sounds familiar, it’s because Bitcoin operates in the same way. &lt;b&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Bitcoin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; is the first example of Blockchain in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;REFERENCES:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“What Is Blockchain Technology? - IBM Blockchain&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;IBM.” Ibm.com, 2021, www.ibm.com/topics/what-is-blockchain.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‌Wikipedia Contributors. “Blockchain.” Wikipedia, Wikimedia Foundation, 16 Oct. 2021, en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
