<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Dhruv Doshi</title>
 <link href="https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/blog/"/>
 <updated>2021-10-16T20:21:30-03:00</updated>
 <id>https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/blog</id>
 <author>
   <name>Dhruv Doshi</name>
   <email>dhruvdoshi25071999@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>What is Blockchain ?</title>
   <link href="https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/blog/2019/08/31/what-is-blockchain"/>
   <updated>2019-08-31T00:00:00-03:00</updated>
   <id>https://dhruvdoshi.github.io/blog/2019/08/31/What-is-Blockchain-!</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot;&gt; 

Blockchain is the technology which allows the user to create the decentralized system of transaction and data transfers. Saying more on, for the naïve person it is a method to create a people’s bank without centrals banks! Blockchain technology is used in backend for each cryptocurrency. Talking about that, Blockchain is creating the blocks of every significant data and then chaining the blocks. So if the last block or any previous block is changed or updated then every information in the chain need to be updated. This makes blockchain technology secure and more robust compared to other technologies.
&lt;br /&gt;
Blockchain is shared, immutable ledger that felicitates the process of recording transactions and tracking assets in business network. An asset can be tangible (a house or a car) or intangible (Intellectual property, patents or copyrights). Virtually anything of value can be tracked and traded on a blockchain network, reducing risk and cutting costs for all involved.
&lt;br /&gt;
Finally, Blockchain is growing list of records, called blocks that are linked together with cryptography which is also described as “trustless and fully decentralized peer to peer immutable data storage which is spread over the network of participants often referred to as the nodes. Every block contains cryptographic hash of previous block and the timestamp and the transaction data in it. 
&lt;br /&gt;
But first, lets get back to basics. What is blockchain and how do it work?

A blockchain is a file for storing data. Or, to put it in  more technical terms, it’s an open, distributed database systems . The data is  distributed (i.e. duplicated) across many computers, and the whole  blockchain is completely  decentralized. This means no one person or entity  (say, a government or corporation like Google or Microsoft ) has control over the blockchain;  this is a radical departure from the centralized (Government data bases) databases that are  controlled and administered by businesses and other entities.
&lt;br /&gt;
So how does it work? In very simple terms, the file is comprised of  blocks of data, with each block being connected to the previous block with the hashing code,  forming a chain. Hence the name ‘blockchain’. As well as the data  itself, each block also contains a record of when that block was created  or edited it contains the hash code of the previous block , which makes it very useful for maintaining a detailed system  of record that cannot be corrupted or lost and this the the major use case to maintain the integrity of the data .
&lt;br /&gt;
 Because the whole blockchain is duplicated across many computers,  any user can view the entire blockchain in the case of public blockchains. Transactions or records are  processed not by one central administrator, but by a network of users  who work to verify the data and achieve a consensus, these verifiers are known as miners, each miner is paid some sort of cryptocurrency for successful mining. If this sounds  familiar, it’s because Bitcoin operates in the same way. In fact, Bitcoin is the first example of blockchain in action.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;REFERENCES:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“What Is Blockchain Technology? - IBM Blockchain&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;IBM.” Ibm.com, 2021, www.ibm.com/topics/what-is-blockchain.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‌Wikipedia Contributors. “Blockchain.” Wikipedia, Wikimedia Foundation, 16 Oct. 2021, en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
